This is my kitchen table and also my
filing system.
Over much of the past three decades,
I've been an investor the highest
calling of mankind I've often thought
was private equity.
And then I started interviewing.
Oh, I watch your interview with coach.
I know how to do something.
I've learned in doing my interviews how
leaders make it to the top.
I asked him how much you want.
He said to 50.
I said, Fine.
I didn't negotiate with him.
I didn't know due diligence.
I have something I'd like to sell and
how they stay there.
You don't feel inadequate now because
being only the second wealthiest man in
the world, Is that right?
Every American remembers where they were
on January six, 2021.
But no American probably was more at the
center of attention on that day than
Mike Pence.
I had a chance to sit down with him to
talk about the epic events of January
six, 2021.
His career as a lifelong political
figure and his current activities.
You've been a governor of Indiana for
ten years, a member of Congress from
Indiana and vice President United States
for four years.
So are you thinking about possibly
running again or you've had enough
elective offices?
You know, I'm a I like to say I never
say never.
But I can tell you, David, my focus
right now is really on trying to be a
voice
for the conservative values that have
really animated my career over the last
40 years and the foundation I created
after we left Washington, D.C., called
Advancing American Freedom is really
committed to those.
Those are Barry Goldwater, Ronald
Reagan, George Bush principles that
really also guided the Trump
administration of a strong defense.
Limited government, fiscal
responsibility, traditional values.
And so whatever the future holds for me,
I'm going to I'm going to continue to
seek to be a champion for those
principles that I think have always made
this country strong and prosperous and
free.
So the organization is called Advancing
American Freedom, and it where is it
based?
Is based right here in Washington, D.C..
I live in Indiana.
So I'm a I'm a commuter to Washington.
But I've got a terrific and a growing
team of principled conservative men and
women who
are putting out the kind of work that
other organizations in the past provided
in the city.
When I was in Congress and as a governor
and in our administration.
But there are less of those voices
today.
And so we've we've emerged, I think, as
one of the leading voices for
traditional conservative thought.
And I'm very humbled by that, but also
see a great responsibility to it.
Now, one of the conservative
organizations that's been very popular
among conservatives in Washington for
many years is the Heritage Foundation.
And recently a number of people have
left the Heritage Foundation and joining
your organization.
Was that a surprise to you?
We were very moved that they were
inspired by our example and our
consistent commitment of principle to
come our way.
But
but in another sense, I wasn't that
surprised.
I have seen a shift in the conservative
movement, really, since President
Trump's
return to active politics and ultimately
his successful campaign, where some are
walking away from the Republican Party's
commitment to America being leader of
the free world.
Some are walking away to our commitment
to limited government and even
marginalizing the right to life.
And the folks that came our way.
I saw really as an endorsement of them
wanting to be a part of a team that is
continuing to stand on that broad,
mainstream conservative agenda.
This define the Republican Party for the
better part of 70 years.
Today, as we talk, two issues have
arisen where I would say the Republican
support is not as strong as it has been
before.
One of them deals with Greenland.
Why do you think so many Republicans on
Capitol Hill say don't get involved with
trying militarily to take over
Greenland?
Well, David, I think you just put a fine
point on it, which is what I hear
objections to, is the notion that we
would ever use military force against a
NATO ally.
Denmark is a NATO ally
and Greenland is a part of their,
you know, their title and control, if
you will, as a territory.
I think there's a great case for
acquiring Greenland, and I fully support
the president's ultimate objective.
I think there's a national security case
for it.
The Arctic is becoming enormously
important.
The ability to expand there would be
very important to the United States and
our security interests in the region.
I expect there's also significant
economic interest in terms of mineral
development and what a student of
history you are.
But it was Abraham Lincoln's secretary
of state who was the first one to
recommend that we purchase Greenland.
And so it is an idea, 150 years in the
making.
Let's talk about another issue that
seems to have divided Republicans a bit,
and that's Venezuela with the effort to
take Maduro out.
There are many people on Capitol Hill,
including some Republicans, who think
that a War Powers resolution making
clear what the president's real ability
to do and not do with military troops
should be clarified.
Do you have any view on Venezuela?
Well, when I was serving alongside
President Trump,
he asked me to take the lead from time
to time in South America.
And the president and I were able to
marshal some 60 nations around the world
to recognize him as the legitimate
president of Venezuela.
It was one of the disappointments of our
first term that Maduro survived the
Trump administration.
And so I commend.
President Trump for taking military
action to bring Maduro to justice here
in the United States.
Our armed forces responded brilliantly.
And I think now we have an opportunity
to move Venezuela forward toward free
and fair elections and a restoration of
the kind of market principles that made
Venezuela once the second most
prosperous nation in our hemisphere.
I fully support the president's action.
If it was to go far beyond that, if
there was a direct military
confrontation, I think
the authorization for the use of force
vote in Congress would be appropriate.
But I think at this point, the president
has operated fully within his
responsibility and authority.
Another issue that has, I think, united
some Republicans, maybe in opposition is
some of what President Trump wants to
do.
And I would just be curious if you can
comment on it, is the chairman of the
Federal Reserve Board.
President Trump hasn't been that happy
with him.
And now it appears to be maybe a
criminal investigation of him for cost
overruns supposedly in the Federal
Reserve building as it's being
reconstructed.
Are you surprised that Republicans on
Capitol Hill have said they aren't going
to confirm anybody until this issue
offered to replace Jay Powell, until
this issue is satisfactory resolved?
I don't think that the American people
want
some pristine independence and
untouchable Federal Reserve by the
elected president or the elected
representatives of the American people.
I was disappointed to see the headlines
about subpoenas having been issued.
If there needs to be a review of that
construction project, it seems like that
should happen in an orderly way.
I'm not terribly surprised to see
leading Republicans in the Senate,
you know, express their concern about
that.
Let's hold the Fed accountable.
The president can express his opinion.
I think that new leadership at the
Federal Reserve would be good for our
economy and good for the country.
But I was disappointed to see that
development.
Let's talk about what you will probably
be remembered for for the rest of your
life.
As you know, the events of January, the
six on 2021 will probably be the date
that you will always be remembered for
because you agreed to have a vote count
and you approved the votes that came in
from the states, in effect saying that
you had not been re-elected as vice
president and President Trump had not
been re-elected as president.
And you obviously had a disagreement
with President Trump over that.
Was that the hardest day of your life
because you had to disagree with the
president and also because people were
trying to take your life?
David January six was a tragic day,
but I'll always believe by God's grace
that I did my duty that day to see to
the peaceful transfer of power under the
Constitution of the United States.
But it was a difficult day.
I don't know if it was the hardest day
I've ever faced.
The day my dad left this earth was an
awfully hard day,
and that was not to be compared to those
moments.
But
it was difficult.
And President Trump and I had a
good working relationship for four
years.
I'd like to say he was not just my
president.
He was my friend.
It was a fluid relationship.
The president gave me extraordinary
opportunities to champion our agenda on
Capitol Hill around the country,
represent America, around the world.
So the fact that
we reached an impasse
on on my duty on January six was
difficult, but I thought my duty was
clear in your book.
So help me God.
You talk about the fact that after a few
days after the election was over and you
had the count and President Trump wasn't
happy, but he wasn't going to be able to
stay in office.
You met with him and he didn't yell or
scream or he just had a very friendly
conversation.
Can you recount what that was like?
I think it's because the president and I
have gone our separate ways.
And in the last several years, I think
it comes as a surprise to people to
remember that
we actually parted very amicably on
January 20th,
2021.
But it
unfolded in those days immediately after
January six.
I'll be honest with you, David, you
asked if I were what my emotions were at
the Capitol on January six.
I can tell you I wasn't afraid, but I
was angry.
I was angry at what I saw.
I was angry seeing people,
you know, desecrating
the seat of our government.
I remember thinking, you know, not this,
not here, not in America.
While it was a day of tragedy because of
the Capitol Hill police who were the
heroes of that day.
The violence was quelled
and leaders in both political parties
reconvened at the very same day
and completed our work for the peaceful
transfer of power.
I remember in one of our last
conversations,
he still seemed very dejected and very
down.
And I ah,
I looked at him and I told him and I
said, Well, you know,
I'm praying for you.
And when I got up to leave the meeting a
little bit later,
I said, You know, I guess it's probably
two things that we're always going to
disagree on.
And he looked up faintly from where he
was seated at the dining room table and
said, Well, what's that?
And I said, Well, I get the impression
we're never going to agree on my duty on
January six.
And I said, And
I'm never going to stop praying for you.
And he looked up with a faint smile and
said, That's right, Mark.
Don't ever change.
Let's go back to the beginning of your
career.
You were born in Indiana.
I was.
What did your father and mother do?
Yeah, my dad was a businessman.
He ended up running a gasoline station
business.
But
several hundred stations across southern
Indiana.
Self-made man live the American dream.
My mom was a second generation
Irish-American.
My dad, a combat veteran.
And
I tell people I feel like I grew up on
the footstool of the American dream.
And you growing up, you went to college
where a little college on the Ohio River
in Indiana called Hanover College and
then Indiana University for law school.
But I always had an interest from the
time I was a little boy in politics and
in public service.
I was deeply inspired by the life, the
example of President John F Kennedy and
the Reverend Dr.
Martin Luther King Jr.
And they still inspire me to this day.
Well, after law school, you practice
law, that little law, but then you
actually got a radio talk show and you
became well-known for that, among other
things.
And you were involved in a policy
institute in Indiana.
And then in 1988, I think you ran for
Congress.
And did you win overwhelmingly?
I did not.
We came close and then
not so much two years later.
All right.
So after 88, you lost and you said,
well, what's the best thing to do?
I'll run again in 1990 and you lost
again?
Did So I assume at the end of that
election you said I've had enough of
politics.
Well, or politics had had enough of me.
I had a feeling that
that that dream was gone.
The dream of being the congressman from
my hometown.
So after a gap of ten years from being
elected, trying to be an elected
official, you run in 90 and your 2000,
you won.
I did.
So when you got the Congress, was it as
good as you thought it was going to be?
And was it worth that long effort to get
there?
It was a great privilege for me and a
dream come true.
I never imagined I could be governor of
the state I grew up in or serve as vice
president.
But Congress was the dream of my youth,
and
I'll always consider it to have been,
you know, God's grace in my life first,
that I didn't win when I first ran
because I don't think I was ready.
But at age 40, after spending a lot of
years thinking about what I believe,
learning a little bit better how to
engage people and communicate, I felt
like I was able to arrive in Washington
with a clear idea of the vision that I
wanted to advance and the values and
principles I wanted to carry there from
Indiana.
So after ten years in Congress,
you decided to run for governor of the
state of Indiana.
So let's go to how you became vice
president.
When did you actually realize you were
actually a serious candidate?
And what was it like when you met him
and you had not been an early supporter
of his?
Is that right?
I had not.
In fact, the president often
would enjoy reminding friends that I had
endorsed someone else in the Republican
primary.
Who did you endorse?
Well, you know, as someone in the
conservative movement, I.
I felt very drawn to Ted Cruz's
candidacy.
I said why I was supporting Ted Cruz.
But I also commended Donald Trump
because it was clear to me that he was
making a connection with all kinds of
people across the country who had had
aspirations for restoring our economy
and standing for values and standing
tall again.
And but.
But it was late June when a business
associate of his in Indiana, who's a
longtime friend of mine, and his called
me on the phone, I was walking into the
governor's residence in Indiana and
said, A friend of mine would like to
know if you would like to be
considered
for
the vice presidential nomination.
And I was taken aback.
So when you got elected vice president,
did you enjoy the vice presidency?
Up until the very end?
I never lost the sense of awe.
Every day that my motorcade drove me up
to the White House or when I climbed on
the helicopters to fly to Andrews Air
Force Base to go somewhere around the
country, around the world.
I was always a
small town guy from southern Indiana.
My grandfather got on a boat, stepped
off onto Ellis Island, Dad ran gas
stations, and there I was on January
20th of 2017 with my left hand on Ronald
Reagan's Bible and my right hand in the
air and took the oath of office to serve
as vice president.
And I never got over it.
It was a great sense.
It's a privilege.
But as we said earlier, it didn't end
the way I wanted it to.
But I'll I'll I'll always be grateful
for the privilege and opportunity that
the President Trump and the American
people gave me to serve with president
decides is the decision.
There could be no daylight
between the president and the vice
president.
And I think it's the reason why we
accomplished so much in those four years
who.
What did you do as vice president that
you're most proud of other than the vote
on January six, but presumably you're
proud of having done that.
But what did you think you accomplished
in those four years before the January
6th vote?
There are two things.
Both of them bear upon our national
security.
Number one is the president
tasked me with giving the first major
speech changing
US posture toward China.
A speech I gave in 2018.
The president and I literally worked
through it together.
And essentially, it I think it started
the process that the Trump
administration achieved, which was to
change the national consensus on China,
was to say, after years of hoping that
economic exchange would result in
greater liberalization in China,
we essentially put a marker down and
said
after years of trade abuses,
intellectual property theft, military
provocations, human rights abuses,
that that
those days were over, we're going to
impose tariffs.
We're going to demand that China comes
forward.
And I'm proud that that posture has been
maintained even through the Biden
administration, but now been redoubled
with President Trump's new term.
Now, President Trump, I think it's fair
to say even President Trump would
probably say this is a bit impulsive at
times and he likes to make decisions
pretty quickly by the traditional
standards of Washington, D.C., You
strike me as a more deliberative type
person.
How did you moderate or modulate what
President Trump did or did you not try
to do that?
I did not try and do that.
I have a great sense on the
the role of the vice president is to
help the president be successful
in the presidency that he was elected to
advance.
One of the reasons I think we had a very
good relationship is that I read
something during the transition in 20
early 2017 that Walter Mondale had
written.
He said in this essay, he said,
everyone that comes into the Oval Office
is looking for something.
They're looking for a decision and they
influence a decision.
He said it can't be like that with the
vice president.
So the vice president owes the president
his opinion once and in private,
because I would add to that, apart from
a moral or constitutional principle,
what the president decides is the
decision.
And sometimes he'd slip and he'd say,
what do you think?
What do you think?
Then he'd say, Mike, where are you on
this?
And I'd say,
Let me talk to you later about that.
And he'd go, Oh, right, right, right,
right.
Because he knew what I knew.
And that was there could be no daylight
between the president and the vice
president.
And I think it's the reason why we
accomplished so much in those four
years.
I didn't ask you about your wife.
Was it love at first sight when you saw
her on your part and her part, or how
did you meet her?
Well, it was on my part.
She was less impressed.
Took it, took a little time.
No, I saw her.
She was playing a guitar up in the front
of a church.
I followed her out the back of the
church
one Sunday morning, and then
I walked her out the front of the church
about 18 months later, spent 40 years
together.
And
she is the love of my life, is an
incredible public servant in her own
right and a great teacher, great mom,
great grandmother.
You were born and raised as a Catholic,
and then at some point you decided to
become what's known as a born again
Christian and a Protestant.
So was that difficult to tell your
mother and father that you were changing
your religion?
And what was their reaction?
Well, first, I cherish my Catholic
upbringing, eight years of Catholic
school.
That's really still a foundation in my
life.
I tell people I didn't I didn't leave
the church.
I left religion.
I by the time I got to high school, I
had had some social success.
And I just decided, David, that religion
was a crutch.
Some people needed it.
I wasn't going to judge him for it, but
I didn't need it.
But when I got off to college, I started
to meet some some young men that simply
talked to me about
being a Christian.
And they talked about having a personal
relationship with God through Jesus
Christ.
And it set me on a journey my freshman
year to really begin to study the Bible
and to examine what the Scriptures said.
And it was in the spring of 1978,
sitting on a hillside at a Christian
music festival.
It was like I heard the words for God so
of the world that he gave his only
begotten Son that whoever might believe
in him might not perish but have
everlasting life.
I just remember my heart was broken with
gratitude for what I believe was done
for me on the.
Cross.
And I walked down and I committed my
life to Jesus Christ.
And
it was
changed my life forever.
And when you talk about that fateful day
in January, five years ago, David, for
me, the essence of that and it's the
reason it's the title of my book, is
that when I took that oath of office,
I believe that I was making a promise to
the American people.
But also it ended with a prayer.
So help me God.
Who?